this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello and welcome to software
engineering radio this is Travis Kimmel
and today my guest is Randy shout Randy
brings 30 years of engineering
leadership experience having worked as a
senior technology leader and executive
at companies of all sizes including
stitch fix Google and eBay brandi is
currently the VP of engineering at we
work and is particularly passionate
about the Nexus of culture technology
and organization Randy's also been
interviewed on SU radio three times in
the past the most recent episode with
Randy was published in 2014 on the topic
of hiring in the software industry Randy
thank you for joining sovereign radio
again thanks Travis yeah happy to be
back for the fourth time so you uh
you're quite a significant influencer in
the DevOps movement so I thought we
would open with sort of your view on how
you've seen that space evolve over time
yeah great I am honored to even be
considered you know one of the
influencers so you know good friends of
mine like Jing Kim and Jes humble Jean
Wyllys they deserve most of the credit
for moving all these ideas forward but
I've been fortunate to have been talking
with them at the times when they were
you know writing the DevOps handbook and
putting together accelerate and so you
know some ideas or more precisely some
of the examples that I've had from the
past have kind of made themselves into
the can and I suppose so yeah so what's
what's DevOps so can I start with what
it isn't and you know if you're if
you're a software vendor you know so
sorry for me to say this but like DevOps
is not about tools and it's actually not
about software infrastructure either
tools are super important and software
infrastructure is super important to but
you know to me DevOps is the application
of maybe the real little a agile
methodologies across the entire software
lifecycle another way maybe to say it
would be something like applying you
know lean manufacturing techniques to
we're and it may be another equivalent
way to say it would be what if we
leverage the idea of feedback loops both
small and large and organized our entire
software development around that and to
me DevOps is kind of all three of those
things and you can see that I'm not a
vendor that I don't have like a canned I
can definition but but to me it's again
applying agile and lean methodologies to
software but applying it in an
end-to-end way so what does that look
like in practice I mean I guess let's
take a step back and contrast it just
for a moment so you know true the
traditional kind of Enterprise II
software development approach which you
know thirty years ago thanks a lot I
started in the industry doing this type
of software so like you'd have the set
of people that come up with the idea so
that's maybe business people or product
people and then you'd have a set of well
paid typist so you know me maybe they
would be software engineers like I was
then there might be a quality set of
people that like figure out did my
typing produce quality software and then
at the end of the day there's going to
be some other people that operate the
software in the real world like that's
traditional software and what we've
learned over those thirty years is that
that doesn't work very well it's much
better to have in one team the people
that have the idea that people that do
the typing maybe maybe people that do
quality or certainly the people that are
responsible for the quality and the
people that operate the software all in
one team and so a bunch of the places
that I've worked where I would claim we
practice DevOps you know Google for
example in stitch fix we in both those
cases we had we call them full stack
teams cross-functional teams that owned
a particular you know piece of software
like an application or a service and
owned it completely end-to-end from the
idea of it all the way through to the
operation of it in in the real world
awesome and can you break down
composition of a cross-functional team
like what does that mean who's on that
yeah sure I mean the honest has with any
good it's a great question
and because it's a great question the
answer is it depends but I'll tell you
what it depends on so if I'm going to
build you know Gmail or something with
that which I didn't do but like
colleagues of mine at Google built Gmail
and the people that would be involved
you know the cross-functional teams that
would be involved in building Gmail
would include people that do the
front-end stuff would involve people
that do we'll call it the application
layer stuff and people maybe that would
do the persistent storage related stuff
and would also kind of operate the
software in the real world and those
those examples that I gave those don't
need to be different individual people
although it's perfectly legit if they
are individual people but the key idea
is that within that team boundary all of
those skillsets are there so notice a
few things I didn't say so I didn't say
people that built the operating system
people that racked and stack the
hardware and one of Google's data
centers
I didn't say people that built chips so
when we say full stack and I'm you know
using my air quotes for a full stack
like we really nobody really means all
the way down to legitimately but you
know really the silicon but the way I
would the way I would say it in general
is who needs to be on the team it's all
the skill sets you need to get the job
done and what's the goal of integrating
all that into one team is it sort of
avoiding this weird resource allocation
problem that you run into otherwise or
is there a host of goals that the
disolves work that's a great question
the fundamental like meta goal is to
reduce the feedback cycle right so we're
all you know again contrasting it to
like traditional old-style enterprise-e
Waterfall approaches to software like
you'd have an idea and then you produce
some big spec and you know maybe a year
later you'd produce something that has
customer value and now the idea is that
we want to be able to have ideas test
them or deploy them and learn from them
in a much much tighter cycle and so the
way that we have learned as an industry
to do that is by co-locating all those
skill sets together and turning like a
waterfall set of handoffs kind of
pipeline process into a more again like
a cross-functional team where
everybody's all working together does
that make sense
it does and when you say colocation just
clarification here for the audience is
that physical colocation how important
do you think that is or is it more kind
of you know the team all reports the
same person yeah I mean I guess it can
be the colocation I don't take that too
seriously like what I meant is put
forming the team out of out of all those
different skill sets I mean I'm happy to
discuss it but it's a different question
about whether people are all co-located
in one physical space or maybe spread
out among among the world and actually
since you asked that I'm in a sidebar on
that for just a little bit then we'll
get back to you know your mainline stuff
so in my experience there are two ways
of configuring an effective team one is
to have everybody co-located in the same
physical space I mean that's when people
say co-located that's usually what they
mean and that was you know we had
definitely teams like that at Google and
it stitch fix and other places at the
other end of the spectrum I've seen
fully remote teams where maybe nobody
works in the same physical space and so
you know stitch fix is also an example
of doing that basically every
open-source project on the planet for
the most part behaves like that right so
clearly lots of great software can be
built in this entirely remote model the
one that doesn't work is that middle
ground where there may be half or more
than half of the team like in the same
physical space with a few maybe one or
two outliers that don't work there and
that's because when people are together
in a physical space humans are social
animals and they tend to like talk about
things very casually and you like you
know just grow up on the whiteboard and
sketch something and then it's like oh
yeah well we better remember to tell
Travis about the architecture discussion
that we just had you know I'm saying I'm
like anybody who's had that experience
of being that one remote person like you
know what I'm talking about and that's
and that's the thing that doesn't work
but notice what I'm not saying I'm not
saying remote doesn't work I'm saying
partially remote doesn't work what
totally works however is everybody
working at least as if they were remote
and so it's stitch fix for example where
I was for you know two years we had a
majority remote engineering teams
a bunch of people were at our
headquarters in San Francisco but they
were the minority of engineers and the
majority of them were mostly working
from their homes all around the United
States and we would form teams you know
that included maybe several people in
San Francisco and other people that
weren't in San Francisco and the key
thing was that the people that were
co-located in the headquarters had to
behave as if they were remote what does
that mean that means like communicating
over a chat like slack doing meetings
always with the videoconference you know
like blue jeans or a zoom or a hangouts
or something like that it means a little
bit more writing and a little bit less
talking you know what I mean like a
little more write something down in a
Google Doc or you know sketch something
out in some online way as distinct from
you know going up on a whiteboard and it
also meant pairing like we did a ton of
pairing even remotely and so there's a
bunch of you know great technologies to
use for that to like screen hero and
others anyway does that make sense like
as long as everybody in that one of
those teams behaves as if they're remote
it totally works and what doesn't work
again is the mostly co-located a few
outliers because then you're you're like
you're fighting against what humans like
to do which is if everybody's in the
same place the same place they just hang
out yep I'd love to dig into the pairing
thing you touched on briefly if pairing
is a new concept to somebody listening
what's the chief goal okay yeah I mean
pairing has been around for as long as
software maybe the words you know or
maybe as old as extreme programming
maybe older than that so like that's at
least 20 years but yeah a lot of people
in their normal software lives maybe
haven't yet paired with somebody else
so I imagine just if you haven't done
this imagine what happens when there's
some bug in your code and you call
somebody over and you help and they help
you try to figure it out that's what
pairing right so you and I Travis could
be pairing together on you know some
particular problem you're trying to
solve or out as you're trying to
remediate or you know thing you're
trying to get an answer to and then just
that's writ large so you know at stitch
fix and it we work and Google you know
it's a it's a pretty common practice to
have engineers pair with one another and
so there's lots of different ways to do
it you know if you're doing it remotely
each of us obviously has our own key
in our own computer but like we use a
shared workspace if you like so you know
we both be typing essentially logically
into the same editor if that makes sense
obviously you know if we're in the same
physical location we can pass at the
keyboard back and forth either the
details that aren't super important but
what the key is is that there are
sometimes I think not all times but
sometimes where two rings really are
your two heads really are better than
one and not encouraging as a practice
like when there are difficult problems
to solve where I need somebody else's
brain because maybe they have different
experience than I do because they know
an area of the code that I don't or
whatever that we use pairing as a tool
I'm always curious about that I feel
like this is tendency to think of it as
sort of like double billing which is not
not a great framing you know sometimes
that comes from sort of outside of
engineering and when it really is more
about knowledge sharing right oh yeah no
I mean it's it's one of those I mean
again as you'll see as we talk like I
tend not to be super dogmatic about
anything so right there are people in
the world who will assert no software
should be produced but for software
that's paired I'm not writing anywhere
near that you know strict or religious
about it I also however don't believe in
the we should never pair so I feel like
there are absolutely opportunities where
it's the right thing to do and sometimes
you know it's the right thing to do to
just be myself and I can you know be in
the zone and make forward progress but
yet to your point you know the the meta
point that you that you underline is
when it's a situation of knowledge
sharing where I have maybe part of the
solution in my brain but you have part
of the solution in your brain or your
can come up with it that we that we work
together and the key thing from a kind
of I guess organizational or cultural
practice perspective is making that
really low friction and easy for people
does it make sense like yeah when you
make that low a low barrier to entry
like we're just super easy for me to you
know again if we're into the same
physical space I could just wander over
to your workstation if we're you know
remote from one another and make it
super easy with tool or something like
that you know that's that that's the
thing that you know we as kind of
managers and leaders can can help to do
it but to help move things forward but
yeah
the problem it's trying to solve is the
each of us both of us together are gonna
come up with a better solution or
diagnose the problem more quickly then
each of us alone and again even if
you've never even if you said I'd never
pair have you ever been in an outage and
that's it everybody you know you know
how it is behavior is exactly that
pairing or I think it's also called
swarming you know that's another term
that comes out of a bunch of the DevOps
inspiring literature so swarming on a
problem like you know it's a swarm of
two yep totally so how do you scale this
sort of thing up I mean this idea of a
co-located team where you've got you
know that team can sort of build
anything because you've got all the
pieces there do it it's very tractable
small team working a discrete problem if
you're working on something like you
know Gmail which you brought up
presumably there's a lot of teams in
there and so how do you how do you
organize that at scale totally that's a
great question and the honest answer is
that the Amazons and the googles and the
Netflix's of the world all have like Co
evolved to essentially the same model
which is individual full stack to pizza
teams each of which is responsible for
maybe a service or a small element of an
application but then form the
organization out of many of them right
right so I never worked on Gmail I'm
totally guessing at this but I'd imagine
that there are some small number of
hundreds of developers on Gmail for sure
they're not one team right they're all
part of the female organization but and
again I have no idea how this is
organized but you could certainly
imagine that like there are a bunch of
people that are dealing with the SMTP
side of things which is like the email
protocol and a bunch of people that are
dealing with the storage and a bunch of
people that are dealing with the you
know email search functionality and then
a bunch of people that are dealing with
different aspects of the application
etcetera etcetera so you form this
larger it's like a fractal or like I
want I don't want to say hierarchy
because that implies something different
than I mean but like a fractal
organization where at one level of
granularity there's all of Gmail which
is again I'm making this up maybe 300
people like I don't know and then it's
smaller at like higher levels of
resolution or magnification
they that subdivides into teams that
have smaller focus or more targeted
focus that make any sense
absolutely and how do you when you do
moving from sort of a singular team and
you realize that the team has grown
large you know you're successful how do
you go about breaking that stuff up into
smaller you know sort of two piece of
teams yeah beautiful that's exactly what
I was gonna answer so how do you get
from like the one team where everybody
sits around a conference table to the
Amazon style or you know Amazon sized
with Google size organization so I like
to use the analogy of cellular mitosis
so people maybe remember from high
school biology that like there's a cell
and that cell sub divides into two cells
and then each of those cells sub divides
into two more cells etc etc and sooner
or later you have you know a human or a
monkey or you know blue whale or
something like that but we all start as
one cell
I mean organizations healthy
organizations are that same way we're
like when we're a tiny startup which I
have been at several iterations in my
career we are everybody fits around a
conference table right so letters maybe
you know three of us or five of us or
six of us we all fin around a conference
table we're all one team and we all have
one singular goal which is you know find
a business model find product market fit
make a make a successful you know
product and then at some point we become
I don't know twelve people let's say and
so then it becomes you know we have to
do the mitosis we have to cleave the
team in two I'm making this up but it
could be like you know if it were
something like eBay which I wasn't there
at the beginning but like you could
imagine that you know there was one team
and then you could cleave it into the
buyer side of the business and the
seller side of the business for example
right like if you were doing ooh BRR or
lyft same thing like driver's side right
or side something like that and then at
some point you know you the driver's
side you know work becomes more than a
team's worth of work and then you cleave
that into you know the driver side app
and the driver side administrative part
or something like that the obvious next
question which I'm sure you would ask if
I shut up would be how do you know what
those like lines are right how do you
understand how to how to divide those
teams and the honest answer is that I've
never found that to be a problem so I
have
always found this is not because I'm
magical or I know I know more than
anybody else it's like but in 30 years
of software you always find that there
are always these natural points to
cleave a team into two or three and it
just simply you know cuz when you're a
team when you're like one team that's
like a bit over large at like maybe
eight like you're not actually all
working on one thing you're actually
ending up working on two or three
different things anyway and so typically
they're the the the like natural points
of you know cellular mitosis where we
like divide the cell those those just
come naturally and I've never you know
maybe I'll find it tomorrow but like
I've never found a problem where are on
a team where it was so big it couldn't
be one team but it wasn't obvious how to
subdivide it does it make sense yep the
answer just presents itself kind of it
always presents itself in like you know
maybe I'm insufficiently good at finding
the patterns I've never found a pattern
for how it does it but it always just
has happened and I think it's not
because I'm lucky I think it's just
because like when the team is too large
to be one team that's almost by
definition tells you it needs to be too
and it's obvious how yeah and and what
do you when you say too large
what are you optimizing for is this
speed which is sort of thought of as the
primal good and software or other are
there other things that make a team feel
unwieldy along the way I mean at the end
of the day it's you know let's take a
step back you're not suggesting
otherwise but like the value that we
provide like basically alright our goal
is to like provide as much customer
value as quickly as possible and there
are two aspects to it's not just produce
as much typing as quickly as possible
and it's not produce as much value
independent of time it's like how can I
produce the most value in the least
amount of time essentially right and
when your team is too large with air
quotes that you can't see it slowed down
right like so we're not able to provide
the same amount of value as quickly by
being one team as by being two
independent teams right is there a sort
of a cultural prerequisite that an
organization needs to have in order to
make this kind of fast-moving co-located
team work yeah I mean I mean I think our
sub
things that you're getting at I mean one
is a cultural value around and doing
what I just said like not every sadly
not every engineering organization
thinks about how do I produce the most
value in the least amount of time you
know what I mean like nobody people
don't think about time to value as their
first order concern I mean they should
but sadly a lot of times particularly
you know I'll say there's as an engineer
particularly organizations that are like
maybe lack LED mostly by engineers or
like let's build the foundations for a
year and then let's build the next level
on top of that and you know none of
which is producing direct customer value
but I feel like I lost a sense of the
question here the same time to values is
super fascinating I feel like along that
route lies a little bit of pain you know
the the MVP that gets kicked out the
door is never gorgeous and yeah yeah so
you know a minimal Viable Product that
comes from Eric Ries and the Lean
Startup he's done a great job of like
that meme lots of people have heard that
name the the wonderful idea and I really
like it by the way I think when people
critique an MVP it's because for the
most part they haven't hit all of those
three elements like they've hit the
minimal element but they haven't hit the
viable element do you see what I'm
saying yep so I mean one part is when we
release the first version of our
startups thing it should be minimal but
it also should be viable right and if
viable means I need to spend two years
probably
it wasn't minimal of that you know or
maybe we bit off more than we can chew
but at the same time it shouldn't be
something totally terrible that nobody
should use the other thing which you
imply which I totally agree with is and
I'm not gonna get this quote right but
somebody very smart who I'm
misremembering said something like if
you're not embarrassed by the first
version of your software you waited too
long to ship that I totally believe as
well right so like it should be a little
rough around the edges that's that's the
minimal part but the key is that it's
viable in other words that there is a
business model there that you have
product market fit that you're the thing
that you do actually is is solving a
real need
and the thing that is the yin and yang
or the like you know the thing you need
to sail between I guess is the under
engineering and which means that it's
not viable but the other side is the
over engineering of not minimal enough
and like waiting too long to ship losing
maybe the market opportunity over
building over engineering and to be
honest I have seen in my experience I've
seen way more of the over engineered
solutions than I have the under
engineered if that makes any sense so I
guess if I had to like top a couple of
levels up the conversational stack one
of the main cultural values is this idea
of minimalism and the idea of iterating
to the solution right so the idea that
we're not going to get it right the
first time and we shouldn't try but at
the same time we should try to get an
8020 rule of there is an actual problem
that we're solving we're solving the
most minimal and straightforward way and
also we're gonna recognize you know as a
team and an organization as a business
we're gonna get a rate on it and make it
better and like I think all those things
are again coming back to how we started
those are all ways that as a culture and
as an engineering organization talking
about those feedback loops right so like
we're gonna produce a minimal Viable
Product we're gonna get some feedback
from our initial set of customers we're
gonna iterate and you know continue to
refine that product hopefully get more
customers hopefully at some point you
know we'll start to scale and have more
and more and more customers and then
we'll be in you know yet different
regimes of things we need to care about
so since feedback is such an important
piece of this what do you view is a good
arbiter of viability like we got it out
there people are using it maybe they
paid for it they may be a little mad
that it's rough around the edges like is
that a win I mean if people find it
useful it is a win right so you know
again the quote that I don't remember
who it applies to and I'm not you know
reproduce incorrectly but the if you're
not a little bit embarrassed you waited
too long you know well we're in this
minimal Viable Product regime if we
release something and everybody is like
wow that's the most polished thing I've
ever seen like you know you should have
really surly and also there's the other
end of the spectrum which is if you
pissed everybody off
when you made them angry that it doesn't
actually do what you said or it's not
reliable like okay maybe it wasn't
viable enough and so you mean your
question is a good one about like how do
you shoot those Rapids how do you let go
between those two and the honest answer
is it depends but but in particular its
what kind of feedback are you getting
from those initial customers right so
are they saying it's terrible and it's
unusable okay you released too soon or
you didn't prioritize the viability
aspect if what they're saying is it's
fine but these things could be better
awesome that's exactly the regime you
want to be in and now you can iterate
and improve those things that were what
we're bad you know one obvious example
that you know is early Twitter right you
know the the meme about Twitter or
particularly early days was the fail
whale but Twitter found this niche this
thing you know met this need that maybe
people who didn't even know they had but
met it sufficiently well not perfectly
well but sufficiently well that even
though there was the fail way all the
time people kept coming back right and
that's a great example of things that
that Twitter was able to iterate around
and by the way you people probably know
but like the history of Twitter was like
it was built really fast and loose in
you know the world's largest rails
monolith and then over time is like
iterated itself to you know rebuilding a
bunch of the stack and microservices and
like that's a wonderful that's a that's
the perfect example of like the
progression you'd want and were the
initial things like a little under
reliable yeah where people in retrospect
a little embarrassed about them yeah
sure but like total product market fit
you know it was filling a need that
people had in the world even if they
didn't know about it and you know
survived as a business and they earned
the right to like rebuild it better and
better and better if that makes any
sense that's a good way to surface this
the feedback do you get sort of internal
to the engineering team that's a great
way to ask that question so I'll answer
it in the way that if you have four and
your team's around a particular business
problem right so like my team is the is
the team that solves the I don't know
access to we work stay
this problem or the room booking problem
or the if I if you form a team around a
particular goal that actually matters to
your customers or end-users then it's
actually really easy to know where the
feedback goes it goes right to the team
you know it's you know I'm saying me
meaning no disrespect but like that
question comes from a place where you
didn't have teams in that way you know
they note you're laughing already
because you know what I'm talking about
that question comes from a place that
said engineering was over here product
or business was over there right right
and only product and business like
didn't understood the customers or
received the feedback and so again no
disrespect but like that question comes
from an organization that I would have
gone and improved in the way that we
just talked about you know I'm saying
like I would have formed smaller teams
not like here's product and business
over here here's engineering and
operations over here I would have put
those teams together more vertically
aligned along real customer needs and
then it's really obvious where the
feedback goes is like the feedback from
the thing that the team produces goes
right to that team by definition almost
so walk us through that a little bit
because I think part of it is that we've
all been on these teams where there's a
lot of siloing and that kind of how do
you go about order sort of the first
steps you do to break that stuff down
and is this like a if the team is
targeting I don't know they pick
something like uptime or page loads or
whatever put that on a monitor how do
you go from the silo state to a better
State yeah that's an excellent question
I will give you an answer but like the
real answer is go and read accelerate
you know otherwise but like accelerate
which is you know Nicole for scrim with
also Jess humble and with Jean Kim that
book is all about answering this
question and the other questions so like
if you're listening to me talk like stop
pause this go read you know go read that
book and come back but so like so now
I'll answer in now I'll answer the
question with that footnote I mean again
as with all things it kind of depends it
depends on why the organization is
siloed and why it's not really working
I mean I've I've been in a bunch of
organizations where I've gone through
and I hate this term but like
through a kind of transformation in this
way where it started out siloed and then
we work together to try to make it into
a more healthier more generative
organization so again I'll always start
with what problem are we trying to solve
so sometimes the first order problem is
like you imply the software isn't
doesn't perform well or isn't reliable
and like okay we can do stuff with that
but the more fundamental problem are
about siloing is that the organization
isn't aligned to customer needs right
like it's you know there's one part of
the organization that cares about
customers but maybe isn't involved in
engineering and we call those people
product or business or something like
that and then there's this other part of
the organization that's siloed over here
which is like the engineers and the
operators of the software and so first
and foremost what I like to do is reform
the organization along the lines that we
just described so what would that mean
that would mean taking the I don't know
20 people or a hundred people or 200
people and rather than having them be in
this siloed more pipeline approach
instead form teams that include people
that have ideas and our product manager
II folks with people that are engineers
and operators and again those don't need
to be separate people but if you're
coming from one of these siloed
organizations usually they are separate
people and forming those teams that are
in this roughly the two Pizza team size
so people you know people who are
listening have probably heard credited
to Jeff Bezos this Amazon idea of two
Pizza teams where no team should be
larger than can be fed by two large
pizzas and the little the little bracket
Astra's thing I'd like to say is I was
talking about DevOps in Cuba earlier
this year I was invited to speak at the
essentially the national computer
science conference in Cuba called
informatica iguana and I was telling
them in Spanish by way about DevOps and
a bunch of these ideas and I had to stop
and explain so if you don't know what
pizza is but but they have like Italian
style individual pizzas so they were
like what do you need two Pizza team
that does make sense
but like no American pizzas are this
size and I had to explain that what was
negative and they got an eight and they
had a big laugh at you know the
overeating American wonderful people by
the way anyway so two Pizza team right
so maybe that's
you know anywhere from like four or five
six people so you you know form teams of
that size and again to our earlier point
like you keep trying to subdivide the
problems in such a way so that each
problem seems to be roughly team sized
if that makes any sense and you might
think it's weird to start with the
organization but there's actually lots
of good kind of organizational behavior
reasons to start with organization
rather than starting with the practices
people maybe are familiar with Conway's
law so mell Conway in 1968 software
engineer actually brilliant guys still
around with us gives great keynotes Mel
Conway wrote this idea up in 1968 that
the organization of a software
organization is directly reflected in
the architecture that they build so more
precisely the architecture that we build
is a reflection of the communication
paths who's communicating with them in
the organization which is kind of
roughly the organization structure
typically and so an interesting
corollary of that idea that your
architecture is going to flow from your
organization is that if you want to have
an architecture that's built out of
small components maybe we'll call them
micro services we could talk about that
later but if you want to have an
organization that's built in small
components one of the first things that
you can do is to construct your
organization out of these small teams
because the organizational structure and
the architecture tend to be like duals
or reflections of each other and
actually interestingly that's the thing
that I'm actively doing right now with
with some of my teams that we work is
like reforming organization in a way
that like more directly reflects the
software that we build and so pretty
managers fit into this picture and how
should they spend their time awesome
question so in a generative organization
one of these like really healthy
organizations a manager's job is to
remove roadblocks from in this case
engineers or remove roadblocks from
their team members more generally so in
unhealthy organizations which I've
worked in by the way the manager's job
is seen as like controlling or
micromanaging the employees
and that is a very unhealthy place to be
it doesn't produce people's best work
it makes people fearful and unproductive
the idea that comes from I'm blanking on
the guy's name Doug Douglas forget his
name but the human side of enterprise is
the name of the book in 1960 and he
posited this idea of Theory X and Theory
Y and I really hate those terms but
those are the terms that exist in the
world
Theory X organizations and people are
like have this view that you know
individuals can't be trusted they need
to be told what to do and as a
consequence they need to be micromanaged
Theory why on the other hand believes
that people are intrinsically motivated
like the genuinely most people want to
try to do a good job they want to
perform well and the job of management
in those organizations is essentially to
get out of people's way help to remove
roadblocks to support them and that's
where these ideas of kind of servant
leadership come from and so what's the
job of management in a healthy
organization it's to do that it's to
help to make as productive as possible
the existing people in the team so help
them to grow up and to learn remove
roadblocks from whatever is preventing
them from moving forward and also
frankly to grow the team right so in
high-growth organizations like we work
for example or stitch fix but also you
know Google and Amazon and Netflix
one of the huge jobs of management is
actually to be recruiting and hiring and
growing team overall but does that make
sense like the primary job for a manager
is to figure out how they can make their
team most productive it's not to tell
them what to do it's to make it possible
for them to do what they already know
how to do how much time should managers
spend communicating the success of the
team sort of external to the team it
seems like another kind of manager level
responsibility on a lot of teams sort of
showcasing success do you ever give an
opinion on that yeah I mean I do I'm not
sure I have an opinion on how much time
to spend but that's not really what
you're asking you're asking like is that
part of the job and I think it is and to
be honest continue if I want to talk
about feedback one of the pieces of
feedback that I've gotten myself and I
need to work on myself is to be better
about that stuff to be better about I
guess trumpeting or recognizing or
celebrating the successes of my
so that's like a that's a that's
definitely a you know an area of
improvement for me overall but ya know I
think that's a really important thing is
and it sounds a little a little
unsatisfying but like to be a
cheerleader for the team you know what I
mean - I mean part of helping the team
be productive is to feel like they're to
feel proud of what they've done and also
again to your point to communicate the
successes and the failures by the way of
the team in a productive way you know
outside of that team and you're not
suggesting otherwise but I think a
healthy organization not I think I it
strongly is true in my experience that a
healthy organization we can celebrate
both failures and successes successes
because we did a thing and we moved a
metric in the right way and we make
customers happier failures because
hopefully we learned something right yep
and almost certainly you know okay we
learned one way not to do it and there's
a wonderful quote from from Edison which
I won't be able to reproduce but it's
something like every one of the thousand
ways I've tried just showed me one way
that didn't work or I won't get the one
cut the word incorrectly but like you
know there's a reason why Edison and
other you know great inventors were able
to like continue to produce great work
it's because they didn't let failures
slow them down or or discourage them or
you know they didn't stop at the first
like imagine if Madison had stopped at
the first time he wasn't able to make
something work like we wouldn't have the
phonograph we wouldn't have the electric
light block like all that stuff right
none of those things happens on a
waterfall schedule you know the first
time anyway so yeah I strongly agree
with you that the what spide your
question which is you know one of the
managers jobs about making the team more
productive is to celebrate that team do
you typically see in addition to kind of
I guess for lack of a better term
classic management that's largely
internal facing and you know people
facing do you typically see teams also
have a dedicated product management role
yeah so I'll say two things I'll say
those two pizza teams within that team
boundary there absolutely is sure I'm
not sure
to phrase this there's product in there
right and a way to do that is to have a
person whose full-time job it is to be
the product manager that is a totally
legitimate solution to that problem
another totally legitimate solution to
that problem is the six people or
whatever that are in that boundary they
share that responsibility in some way
but they they together come up with what
the roadmap is and what the
prioritization is and so on and I've
seen both of those ways work work well
so I'm not gonna I've certainly wouldn't
claim that one is better than the other
but either way totally works so it
stitch fix for most of the time that I
was there we did not have dedicated
product managers and it was mostly
individual engineers working directly
with business people or directly with
customers that ended up helping us to
figure out what the roadmap for
individual teams was and that works very
well I've also worked at other
organizations like Google for example
which had a very strong product
management function and those product
managers that were essentially assigned
individual teams and organization
provided great value so the thing that I
think is the invariant is that within
the team boundary there is a product
management function and I'm agnostic to
be honest about how that responsibility
is like allocated to the people in the
same way by the way as within that team
boundary there should be an Operations
function like assuming you're building
something that's online like within that
team boundary somebody should be
operating the software now I do have
strong beliefs that we should be
rotating the Patriot right everybody
but like another solution to that
problem is to have one person that's
like an Operations expert or something
like that does it make sense to me the
from it from an outside organizational
perspective I want to make sure as like
a leader of teams to make sure that
within the team boundary they have that
kind of accountability and that
ownership and that ability to do that
whether it's product or producing the
software engineering or operating the
software like all those things are
within that boundary so in the more
distributed model for product management
what is the equivalent of rotating the
page what does that look like in action
is it every engineers is taking some
customer calls or you know just kind of
tactically in the example
we're a team didn't have a dedicated
product manager how would they do it I
think there are lots of ways to do it
I'll give you the specific you know
template or model that we had at stitch
fix so stitch fix is a clothing retailer
and so we maintain physical warehouses
around the US where we stored stuff and
I had an engineering team that built the
warehouse software doesn't matter the
details but there's a function of
styling we're like for customer for a
particular customer deciding what
clothes to send them in the box I had a
team that built software for the
stylists and then we had a bunch of
other teams for you know building
software for the customer support people
etc in all those examples again for most
of the time that I was there we didn't
have dedicated product management and so
the warehouse software team would just
work with two warehouse people right so
there were not all 2,000 them but there
was a small team on the business side of
the warehouse group that were more or
less product managers land they were
basically two people but they were
inwardly focused on on the warehouse and
they were the ones that figured out what
kind of tooling would help the warehouse
employees to be happier and more
productive etc and essentially that team
would be the team that we would interact
with as engineers and then ditto on the
styling side there was you know an
organization of the stylists and then
there were there ended up being a team
on the business side that more or less
figured out how to enable the stylists
to be more productive and again that was
a set of people that we would interact
with but the general model is in that
example where there wasn't a dedicated
product manager with that title in their
roll title on there you know mystic art
or whatever we would have engineers
working directly with either customers
or somebody that represented customers
and so do you do like sort of a rotating
model where someone's kind of on deck
for outreach yeah it wasn't really I
mean it wasn't like that
I suppose I could imagine something like
that it wasn't like we rotated who was
gonna take the customer calls although
like that's a legitimate thing to do and
by the way if you were a small start-up
with six people left that's probably
what you would do right
you would probably rotate among
everybody who's gonna take the customer
calls both of those examples I used were
software that we were building for other
employees and so there was already a
dedicated team that
for better or worse their job was to
figure out what those thousands of
people needed to do their jobs right so
like we could do the wreck with that and
we didn't need yet another you know
mediary one of the things that you
touched on briefly in that you speak
quite a bit at conferences about is to
say this transition from monolith to
micro services can you elaborate a bit
on what that looks like and maybe how
that fits into the broader story of
scalable high quality resilient software
so let me take a tiny step back and say
that by strong belief and my experience
is that different phases of a product
and different phases of a company tend
to be better served by different types
of software so very cool I mean I'll
give you a better answer than this but
like a single monolith couldn't do
Google or Amazon in the moment and also
the five-person startup shouldn't be
building a thousand micro services so
like that's both of those things are
both those statements are pretty obvious
if you stop to think about it so clearly
if you take a step back there's this
progression or this you know these
phases of a company or a product or
whatever we're at each individual phase
there might be a different way of
solving the problems so the way I like
to lay it out is hard to do this without
a diagram but if you think of all
companies and products sort of follow
this s-curve people talk about a J curve
by the way J curve is just what you
haven't seen the full end of the S make
you know what I'm buying that so
everything is an S curve so it get
starts out a little bit small so like
you have your tiny little startup and
you have a few initial customers and
your growing onesie twosie
and then at some point if you're lucky
you might start to hit a scaling phase
where customers are coming really
rapidly and so you know eBay's
experienced this and Google and Amazon
and Netflix have all experienced this
kind of scaling phase and then often you
know you'll have what I'll call the
optimizing phase but that's the top part
of the S curve where it kind of flattens
out a little bit and it's growing slowly
again so it's starting phase scaling
phase optimize phase so in the starting
phase you really are just trying to meet
the near-term needs of your small set of
customers and so you want to iterate
really rapidly and so riots and
organizations that are in that regime
tend to adopt these like rapid
prototyping frameworks so like PHP is
really common or rails like you know
those are just common frameworks that
people would use in those areas doesn't
make them right or wrong but but notice
what they're trying to optimize for
they're trying to optimize for rapid
developer productivity and they're
trying to optimize for iteration what
they are not trying to optimize for is
massive scale
right and it's totally legit by the way
to build a monolith in that phase like
totally legitimate at some point you may
grow and scale enough that the monolith
that you run out of gas on your monolith
either because of feature velocity so
your teams are stepping on each other's
toes and everybody's in one codebase and
they're not able to make any forward
progress people have probably
experienced that I certainly have also
there's other examples like in the eBay
Google and Amazon examples where a
monolith doesn't physically scale if
that makes any sense like from the
perspective of load or perspective of
latency so breaking up that monolith
into smaller pieces is the thing that
you want to do but before I go on to
talk about microservices I want to say
that like probably 90% or maybe 95 or
99% of applications in the world are
best served by a monolithic application
it's the exception rather than the rule
where you need to build a distributed
system and build things out of these
things that we might call micro services
so I just want to stop there so it's not
like every company or product
necessarily evolves to micro services
but in my experience past a certain
scale every one of those big companies
that we know and respect so the googles
the Amazons the eBay's the Netflix as
the Twitterers blah blah blah all of
those have co-evolved not because they
talk to each other but co-evolved to
something that we now call micro
services so micro services are a
solution to the scaling phase not to be
like starting or like steady-state
initial phase it's only when you're
doing that rapid scale and you need them
okay so with that as the background to
what I'm about to say I will talk about
what does that transition point between
the monoliths and the microservices look
like okay so again I mentioned a couple
of like warning signs or reasons why you
might notice that your model if is
running out of gas so the first one
again is feature velocity so that's at
least the phrase that we used to use at
eBay
where the team is not able to sustain
its earlier productivity because
everybody's all stepping on each other's
toes and the in the Model S and another
kind of equivalent warning sign is like
if you have new people join your team
and it takes them like three months
before they can successfully and
productively add something like that's a
good warning sign that's a terrible sign
but you know what I mean like if when
somebody joins the team if it takes a
months to be productive because there's
all this backstory and oh we have to
make sure you update this and forget
don't forget to not break that thing and
test this weird other edge case that you
didn't think was related like all that
stuff is a good indicator that your
monolith is interrelated and you know
challenge it okay and then again the
other the other common warning sign is
the like load related scaling so maybe
your customer growth or the growth of
the load is such that vertical scaling
of your model if runs out of gas
eBay actually had both of those problems
and midway through its career and both
had the feature velocity problem where
everybody was in the same codebase in
fact the eBay thing was they had built
this the second version of eBay after
the founders like initial prototype was
a C++ this is actually a nice a PD ll if
you know what that is you will be
shuttering when you when you hear that
at its worst it grew to 3.4 million
lines of code in that one DOL 3.4
million lines of code and they were
actually hitting compiler limits on the
number of methods per class which I'm
embarrassed to say actually no the the
number of that which is 2 bytes so
that's 16 K worth of methods that's how
many you could have and they were
actually hitting that compile limit
which is terrible that's incredible it's
incredible yeah I mean it's incredible
to be honest it's incredible that eBay
surest to be honest but they did again
you know what's going down all the time
very difficult for people to be
productive but yet they solved the
customer need and they were able to kind
of earn the right to rebuild it okay so
that was one aspect of it which is kind
of feature velocity so everybody being
not just in the same repo but like in
the same file and in the same class like
imagine how terrible it was so that was
a feature velocity part but similarly
eBay was also hitting kind of load
related scaling as well so eBay in the
early days was in that monolithic C++
DLL but over a monolithic Oracle
database and so it was one big database
that had all of eBay and they could all
be vertically scale that thing so this
was at the time they were buying you
know the largest machines that Sun
Microsystems was manufacturing so at one
point they were on a 72 Way
refrigerator-sized Sun machine and this
probably never happened but I'm kind of
like imagining this thing where you know
one of the eBay guys calls up son there
were like okay we have your 72 a1 ready
for you to send us 144 away and some Sun
reps like we don't have that and so you
know that was a good indicator that eBay
was gonna have to break it up but does
that make sense - like feature velocity
is usually one reason load related stuff
or a vertical scaling is another one a
related one which is rarely anybody's
first order reason but as often
everybody's second order reason is what
I'll call deployment independence so
like being able to deploy different
parts of the system independently of
others right so if you take a step back
like no matter how simple a system there
are typically some parts of the system
that are really fast moving like
typically things that are related to the
UI and there are a bunch of things that
are typically slow moving so like maybe
once you've built your authentication
system that's example I always use like
typically once you've built that
authentication system you're not like
messing with it all the time like it
just works and you don't mess with it
and it's pretty weird so like every time
I'm deploying the JavaScript but I'm
also redeploying the authentication
system like that's kind of weird so you
know another reason why we might break
our monolith up into smaller components
is you know because we want different
parts of the system to evolve at
different rates right because they have
different life cycles essentially
okay so how do I do it there are a
couple of different maybe patterns I'll
say for how you might break that
monolith up one way which people might
have heard about it read about is
something called the strangler pattern
and that comes from the strangler fig
which is like a tree that grows in the
southern hemisphere and a fig gets
dropped by some bird usually at the top
of things seed gets dropped the top of
some other tree like it's not a fig tree
and then that seed sprouts and it grows
down around the other strangling it
that's why it's called the strangler fig
ends up killing that central tree but
like builds its superstructure around
that
host tree and if you've ever seen it's
like a if you don't reach for an abandon
tree like that's what this is or a ficus
which is Latin for fig so if you ever
have a ficus in your house it's those
kind of trees anyway so the strangler
pattern which I think is credited to
Martin Fowler and the ThoughtWorks
people that idea is you have your model
if which is the host tree and you put
some proxy in front of it and then you
slowly break out pieces of the monolith
but that proxy guy routes some of the
calls to the monolith and some of the
calls to the new component that you
build that make sense conceptually it's
hard to do this without a diagram so
that's a strangler patterns that works
successfully another pattern that I've
seen is is imagine a month imagine a
model earth is like some box and you
find some seam some area that you want
to pull out so maybe it's like the
payment system or maybe it's I don't
know the search part of the site or
something but you find something that's
separable and you build a language
interface around it so like if it's Java
you make it its own jar if it's Ruby and
making its own gem if it's two plus plus
or C sure I can make it its own
interface like whatever is your chosen
language you make some like language
interface around that component and then
you write a bunch of tests don't skip
that step you write a tests around that
component interface to make sure that
the behavior is gonna stay constant when
you do the next thing I'm about to say
and so now that you have that interface
that separates the you know payment part
let's say
from the rest of the system now you can
pull that payment part out into its own
service and you just have the
implementation behind the interface kind
of proxy to the separate service again
this is really difficult to do without a
diagram but I hope that explanation
makes sense
absolutely you taking a black box and
you're removing one piece of it exactly
right yeah you're you're guarding and I
want to give credit where credit is due
that word seam comes from Michael
feathers excellent book which anybody
who's trying to do monolith to micro
services should totally read it's called
I always get the first word wrong I
always remember it as dealing
effectively with legacy code but I think
that's not exactly right but it's by
Michael feathers totally should read
that book by the way when I joined
Google there was one and only one book
that was required reading for people
that join Google and that was it so
strongly recommend reading it and the
reason why I bring that up is because he
introduced this concept of trying to
find that seemed like a seam in your
clothing between you know the chest the
body part of the shirt let's say and
like the sleeve finding that seam and
sometimes you have to refactor to get to
the point where there is that seam where
that is that separation between for
example the payment part of the system
and the rest of the system but once
you've found slash created that seam
then you can build an interface around
it right tests around it and then you
can pull that piece out there's other
techniques to do when the monolith that
you're trying to deal with is a
monolithic database versus a monolithic
application but we can leave that aside
for just a sec yeah so when you we talk
about this seam approach and sort of
crafting a seam to work in is that
typical of monoliths that you've you
know I think we've all sort of had the
experience of getting in there it's just
a bunch of spaghetti code and you kind
of pull a thread and the whole thing
unravels how do you go about allocating
resources to do that how do you fund it
yes yeah that's exactly right so
oftentimes one of the things people talk
to a run into is you know you sort of
come to the table and say hey we'd like
to pay down some of this technical debt
and what the the rest of the
organization hears is like engineering
is taking two months off which is super
uncharitable and not what's going
yeah how do you sort of socialize that
in the width you get support for it that
is a great question and as having been
an engineering leader for a while like
I've faced that basically at every
custody that I've worked out to be
perfectly honest like how do you
essentially fund technical debt
reduction or we architecture or
refactoring or you know all these
different things that are basically
about improvements code quality and
service quality I have seen two
approaches that work one approach is
very explicitly with everybody's
permission fold it into the other work
that we do so when I'm going to add
feature n plus-1 to my application the
implication is that the engineer when
they're going to estimate that or
whatever when they're gonna do the work
of adding feature n plus one they are
going to refactor the system such that
adding feature n plus one is really easy
you fold the REO architecture
refactoring technical debt reduction
work into other work the new stuff is
providing air cover for three factors
essentially yeah and but the key thing
is like not to hide it you know so I've
seen a bunch of organizations where like
yeah we just we don't tell the business
people we just do and like that's good
except you're not hiding the ball and
it's like saying you know what we're
never gonna tell I'm struggling with us
analogy but like you're driving the car
we're just never gonna tell anybody that
you have to go get oil changes or like
replace tires or like really like that
actually cost money and like that's
money that could go to you know buying
food so like why aren't why are you
lying to your spouse or significant
other or family about like I'm secretly
putting gas in the car and secretly
doing oil changes because you know
whatever so like what I don't recommend
is hiding it but a legitimate technique
again like I say is to have just the
cultural expectation that when I'm
adding a new thing that I also refactor
to make that possible now that works
best maybe only when the work that I
would need to do to refactor is within
my team boundary yep this makes sense
what I'm saying so like my team is
working away on
you know my team's features and if I can
do the refactor or the technical debt
reduction within the scope of my team
that will totally work but there are
lots of for example moving from a model
as the Micra services for example like
there are lots of things that cross a
bunch of team boundaries where that
technique doesn't work so the other
technique that I've used effectively is
to essentially agree on a budget for
this type of work with my business
partners so I've done this at unbunch of
companies at eBay this was my idea a
butt like a eBay we had what we called
head room projects where there was a I
forget what it was 20 25 30 percent of
engineering efforts somewhere in there
was set aside for projects that gave us
more Headroom right so like imagine eBay
is continuing to grow grow grow and at
some point they're gonna bump their head
against the ceiling and so the idea was
that that budget would fund productivity
improvements and scalability
improvements that would be chosen by the
engineering team but you know that
budget was set aside for that work and
that's kind of the analogy that I'm
using here at stitch fix we did a
similar thing where for reasons I'm
happy to discuss we were hitting some
limits on the monolithic database that
we had and so it just became very clear
that we needed to fund we called it a
stability and scalability initiative to
start pulling services out of the
monolithic database and breaking it up
and so again we show what I did as you
know the engineering leader at the time
was to go to the executive team lay out
the near-term problems that we were
seeing how they were gonna get worse
over time and explaining ok here I need
your help to like have me set aside a
budget of we said 25 percent of
engineering effort to draw down that
technical debt and to make scalability
in part tivity improvements and that
budget approach works really well
because it allows the business people
and to like agree we can have a
conversation up front about what should
it be 20 percent or 25 or 30 percent or
50 percent like you have that very
explicit mature conversation about what
level of investment are we willing to
make in these reliability and
scalability improvements and at the same
time it doesn't
force this weird situation where the
engineering team for every micro
improvement in scalability or whatever
that they're going and like having to
explain it to people who like are smart
but like
don't care about the detail so that
makes any sense you know what I mean
like correctly see I mean let's say this
way that like if my business partners
didn't trust me to spend that 25 percent
of efforts well they should fire yep
that is literally my job like that's
what I'm trained to do and that budget
approach it's obvious but just to you
know connect the dots that budget
approach works best for these large like
cross-cutting horizontal things where it
does involve a lot of effort from a lot
of different people on a lot of
different teams does it make sense
yeah and underscore is sort of a
recurring theme in our conversation up
front and overt agreements are generally
good yes could not agree more it may not
keep referring to the idea of generative
organizations which comes right out of
accelerate in the DevOps handbook so we
talked about pathological and
bureaucratic and generative
organizations and in these healthy
generative organizations the ability to
have these conversations transparently
and maturely like that's a key aspect
right like if you're not able to talk to
your business partners and explain
here's why the system isn't performing
well here's why it's not reliable and
here's what I would do to fix it here
are the investments that we should make
and if the business partners aren't
receptive to that conversation what
that's bad right and a lot of a lot of
terrible software has been built in
organizations that weren't able to have
mature conversations about long term
engineering viability absolutely all
right well is there anything we haven't
discussed yet that we should have oh
gosh I mean there are so many so many
things but no I think we covered a lot
so that was great I mean I really I
liked
thank you for driving in the way that
you did so we talked about organization
we talked about culture we talked about
practices that we have I mean I guess we
didn't suffer cover a continuous
delivery in any way but you know there
are books about that like literally just
humbled and you know Dave Farley's
continuously read books so we could save
that for another time
okay well thanks for joining us today
Randy cool thanks this is Travis Kimball
for software engineering radio and we'll
see you next time
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening